<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Deniz Johns</title>
    <link href="https://denizjohns.net/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://denizjohns.net" />
    <updated>2026-01-04T16:04:12+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>DJ</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://denizjohns.net</id>

    <entry>
        <title>collective-iz </title>
        <author>
            <name>DJ</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://denizjohns.net/collective-iz.html"/>
        <id>https://denizjohns.net/collective-iz.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/29/coliz-at-lux-2.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Experimental cinema"/>
            <category term="Curatorial Activities"/>

        <updated>2026-01-04T10:44:39+00:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/29/coliz-at-lux-2.jpg" alt="" />
                    In 2012, Deniz co-founded collective-iz in London, with artists and filmmakers Maria&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/29/coliz-at-lux-2.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <figure class="post__image">
<p>In 2012, Deniz co-founded <a href="https://collective-iz.tumblr.com/post/104022177454">collective-iz</a> in London, with artists and filmmakers Maria Anastassiou, Amy Dickson, and Karolina Raczynski. Since then, collective-iz has programmed and produced significant experimental audio/visual events. The collective’s work has been generously supported by the community of experimental filmmakers and writers in London, including A.L. Rees, Annabel Nicolson, Lis Rhodes, Nicky Hamlyn, Guy Sherwin &amp; Lynn Loo, William Raban, Nick Collins, Simon Payne, Cathy Rogers, Vicky Smith; and institutions, such as The Horse Hospital, Lux/London, Riverside Studies, no.w.here, British Artists' Film and Video Study Collection, to name but a few. These events bring together analogue film projection, live-feed performance, and para-cinematic practices, and foster dialogue between emerging and established artists within the historical trajectory of experimental film and video.</p>
</figure>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/29/coliz-guy-lynn.jpg" alt="Lynn Loo &amp; Guy Sherwin performing their RemJet Loops, Black &amp; Light, Apiary Studios, London, 2015" width="770" height="513" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/29/responsive/coliz-guy-lynn-xs.jpg 300w ,https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/29/responsive/coliz-guy-lynn-sm.jpg 480w ,https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/29/responsive/coliz-guy-lynn-md.jpg 768w ,https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/29/responsive/coliz-guy-lynn-lg.jpg 1024w"><span style="color: #686c78; font-size: 0.702332em; text-align: center;">Lynn Loo &amp; Guy Sherwin performing <em>RemJet Loops,</em> Black &amp; Light, Apiary Studios, London, 2015</span></figure>
<p>List of events to date <a href="https://collective-iz.tumblr.com/screeningsEvents">(more detailed programme info/posters/notes here)</a>:</p>
<p>2023  <i>Lights-Move-Morecambe</i>, Jewellers, Morecambe, Lancaster</p>
<p>2020  <i>Home Movie</i>, (moved to online due to the pandemic)</p>
<p>2019   <i>Work </i><i>Programme</i> at LUX, London</p>
<p>2018   <i>Light and Dark Park</i> at LUX, London</p>
<p>          <i>1968 and Its Legacies Conference</i>, King’s College London</p>
<p>2017   <i>Black &amp; Light</i> at Supernormal Festival, Oxfordshire</p>
<p>2016   <i>Portraits</i> at New River Studios, London</p>
<p>2015   <i>Black &amp; Light</i> at Apiary Studios, London</p>
<p>2014   <i>Screenscapes</i><i> </i>at Apiary Studios, London</p>
<p>           <i>Film | Performance | Space</i>, Summerhall, Edinburgh</p>
<p>2013   <i>Now and Here,</i> The Horse Hospital, London</p>
<p>2012   <i>Silents,</i> Hockney Gallery, Royal College of Art, London</p>
<p>           <i>Black &amp; Light Films,</i> Royal College of Art, London</p>
<p>2011   <i>Problems of Protest,</i> Royal College of Art, London</p>
<p>           <i>Performance to the Camera,</i> Royal College of Art, London </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/29/coliz-at-supernormal-Nicky-2.jpg" alt="Nicky Hamlyn, performing his Quadrants (2017) at Black &amp; Light, Supernormal, Oxford (2017)" width="851" height="478" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/29/responsive/coliz-at-supernormal-Nicky-2-xs.jpg 300w ,https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/29/responsive/coliz-at-supernormal-Nicky-2-sm.jpg 480w ,https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/29/responsive/coliz-at-supernormal-Nicky-2-md.jpg 768w ,https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/29/responsive/coliz-at-supernormal-Nicky-2-lg.jpg 1024w"><span style="color: #686c78; font-size: 0.702332em; text-align: center;">Nicky Hamlyn, performing </span><strong style="font-size: 0.702332em; text-align: center;"><em>Quadrants </em>(2017) </strong><span style="color: #686c78; font-size: 0.702332em; text-align: center;">at Black &amp; Light, Supernormal Festival, Oxfordshire (2017)</span></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Returning &amp; Turning</title>
        <author>
            <name>DJ</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://denizjohns.net/returning-and-turning.html"/>
        <id>https://denizjohns.net/returning-and-turning.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/8/Screenshot-2024-12-29-at-11.00.18.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Video"/>
            <category term="Film and video"/>
            <category term="Experimental cinema"/>

        <updated>2025-12-31T11:39:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>t</title>
        <author>
            <name>DJ</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://denizjohns.net/self-portrait.html"/>
        <id>https://denizjohns.net/self-portrait.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/28/IMG_20180820_213850_833.jpeg" medium="image" />
            <category term="photography"/>

        <updated>2025-12-29T20:05:03+00:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/28/IMG_20180820_213850_833.jpeg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <figure class="post__image align-center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/28/IMG_20180820_213850_833-2.jpeg" alt="" width="1834" height="1834" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/28/responsive/IMG_20180820_213850_833-2-xs.jpeg 300w ,https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/28/responsive/IMG_20180820_213850_833-2-sm.jpeg 480w ,https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/28/responsive/IMG_20180820_213850_833-2-md.jpeg 768w ,https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/28/responsive/IMG_20180820_213850_833-2-lg.jpeg 1024w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Media Blackout Series (2016-2021)</title>
        <author>
            <name>DJ</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://denizjohns.net/media-blackout-media-blackout-series-2016-2021.html"/>
        <id>https://denizjohns.net/media-blackout-media-blackout-series-2016-2021.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/16/Screenshot-2025-12-14-at-10.25.38.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Video"/>
            <category term="Film and video"/>
            <category term="Experimental cinema"/>

        <updated>2025-12-29T14:54:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/16/Screenshot-2025-12-14-at-10.25.38.png" alt="" />
                    Media Blackout Series is concerned with the challenges and perhaps the impossibility&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/16/Screenshot-2025-12-14-at-10.25.38.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><strong><i>Media Blackout Series </i></strong>is concerned with the challenges and perhaps the impossibility of video art or any other audio-visual art to communicate complex political truths. Essentially it presents an epistemological concern, what and if can art make us know. </p>
<p>On the one hand, the title refers to actual media blackouts; the first piece, Media Blackout I (2016) was made soon after the state imposed total media blackout following one of the deadliest suicide attacks that happened in Türkiye in 2015. On the other hand, the title is inspired by Adorno’s notion of imageless materialism, negative dialectics and his critique of representation. </p>
<p>The series consist of three video pieces and an expanded cinema performance:</p>
<p><strong><i>A+ </i></strong>(2021) DV, 4’30”, colour, sound</p>
<p><strong><i>Media Blackout III </i></strong>(2018) DV, 3’, colour, silent, loop monitor installation (alternative format: multiple monitor screening on loop)</p>
<p><strong><i>Media Blackout II, </i></strong>(2017) live performance, variable duration</p>
<p><strong><i>Media Blackout I</i></strong><i>, </i>(2016) DV, 4’, B&amp;W, silent (alternative format: multiple monitor screening on loop)</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>AI Art and the Foreclosure of Ecological Agency: A Critique of Refik Anadol’s Echoes of the Earth</title>
        <author>
            <name>DJ</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://denizjohns.net/refik-anadol-take-down.html"/>
        <id>https://denizjohns.net/refik-anadol-take-down.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/9/3DEC4F69-188C-4CE5-A1B2-2D1BF4732CC9_1_105_c.jpeg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Writing"/>
            <category term="Book chapter"/>
            <category term="AI art"/>

        <updated>2025-11-21T11:40:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/9/3DEC4F69-188C-4CE5-A1B2-2D1BF4732CC9_1_105_c.jpeg" alt="" />
                    Johns, Deniz &amp; Zeilinger, Martin (2025) “AI Art and the Foreclosure of&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/9/3DEC4F69-188C-4CE5-A1B2-2D1BF4732CC9_1_105_c.jpeg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Johns, Deniz &amp; Zeilinger, Martin (2025) “AI Art and the Foreclosure of Ecological Agency: A Critique of Refik Anadol’s Echoes of the Earth”, in Vectoral Agents, Eds. Claudio Celis Buena and Jernej Markelj.Institute for Network Cultures, Amsterdam</p>
<p>Abstract: </p>
<p>In this chapter we examine Echoes of the Earth: Living Archive, Refik Anadol’s 2024 exhibition at Serpentine Galleries, and challenge Anadol’s claim that his work fosters ecological awareness and shared agency through AI-driven immersive aesthetics. While Anadol frames the Large Nature Model (LNM), the bespoke AI system underpinning the show, as an “open-source” and “more-than-human” tool capable of giving a voice to nature, we argue that the project ultimately reinforces the opacity, extractivism, and corporate dependencies characteristic of large-scale contemporary AI systems. By analysing the exhibition’s sensory spectacle, associated rhetoric of transparency and “radical clarity,” and misleading claims regarding the “open source” nature of the underlying technologies, we argue that Anadol’s work immobilises viewers instead of activating their ecological imagination – Echoes of the Earth produces a technologically saturated requiem for threatened ecosystems rather than a space for critical engagement. Our chapter situates this dynamic within longer histories of media art, and we contrast the non-reflexive immersion strategies of Anadol’s installations with experimental practices that sought to demystify their technological apparatuses. We also interrogate the LNM’s purported openness, and show how its proprietary infrastructure, selective data disclosure, and monetised platformisation contradict its public-interest framing. Ultimately, opportunities for collective agency or ecological intervention are foreclose, rather than enabled. In closing, we outline alternative trajectories emerging in contemporary AI art that more effectively support ecological imagination and redistributions of agency.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Splinter in my Eye: Structural/Materialist Film</title>
        <author>
            <name>DJ</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://denizjohns.net/splinter-in-my-eye.html"/>
        <id>https://denizjohns.net/splinter-in-my-eye.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/10/978-3-031-55256-4.webp" medium="image" />
            <category term="Writing"/>
            <category term="Experimental cinema"/>

        <updated>2024-11-01T11:46:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/10/978-3-031-55256-4.webp" alt="" />
                    Johns, Deniz (2024) “Splinter in my Eye: Structural/Materialist Film” The Palgrave Handbook&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/10/978-3-031-55256-4.webp" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><strong>Johns, Deniz (2024) </strong>“Splinter in my Eye: Structural/Materialist Film” The Palgrave Handbook of Experimental Cinema, (eds. Kim Knowles &amp; Jonathan Walley) Pelgrave Macmillan (peer-reviewed)</p>
<h3>Abstract…</h3>
<p>In this chapter, I reconsider Peter Gidal's Structural/Materialist film project and its relationship with Marxist political and aesthetic theory. My aim is twofold: first, to ascertain the extent of their alignment; second, to assess if and how the aesthetic strategies Gidal developed -based on Marxist underpinning- remain relevant and useful today. Gidal began developing his concept of Structural/Materialist film in the 1970s, as a radical Marxist materialist film practice that aimed to transform the existing capitalist modes of relations in film production and film viewing, towards dialectical-materialist modes. He developed numerous aesthetic strategies against illusionistic film and its identification processes, which are in line with his anti-narrative and Althusserian Marxist stance. Within this framework, my particular focus will be on three specific strategies that I consider most significant and pertinent to his practice: “the construction of non-identity in the filmic process”; “de-subjectivization” and “the emptying-out of potent signifiers, of meaning”. I explore these concepts through critical readings of <em>Room Film 1973</em> (1973) and <em>Denials </em>(1986) in the context of Marxist political and aesthetic discourse, drawing on key texts by Althusser, Adorno and Jameson, in order to ascertain if they can still be relevant to contemporary film and video practices. While my critique reveals certain flaws and limitations in some of Gidal's aesthetic strategies, I contend that his Structural/Materialist film theory retains significance as a starting point to define the contemporary terms of critical experimental cinema.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Filmer à l’aveugle : une enquête sur l’esthétique marxiste matérialiste de Peter Gidal </title>
        <author>
            <name>DJ</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://denizjohns.net/filmer-a-laveugle-une-enquete-sur-lesthetique-marxiste-materialiste-de-peter-gidal.html"/>
        <id>https://denizjohns.net/filmer-a-laveugle-une-enquete-sur-lesthetique-marxiste-materialiste-de-peter-gidal.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/12/9788869764257.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Writing"/>
            <category term="Experimental cinema"/>

        <updated>2024-10-28T16:19:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/12/9788869764257.jpg" alt="" />
                    Johns, Deniz (2024) “Filmer à l’aveugle : une enquête sur l’esthétique marxiste&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/12/9788869764257.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><strong>Johns, Deniz (2024) </strong>“Filmer à l’aveugle : une enquête sur l’esthétique marxiste matérialiste de Peter Gidal” in <i>Cinematerialisms</i><i>: New Materialist Approaches to the Audiovisual</i> (double-blind peer-reviewed) Médiums Series, Éditions Mimésis, Images: Paris (peer-reviewed)</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>A+</title>
        <author>
            <name>DJ</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://denizjohns.net/a.html"/>
        <id>https://denizjohns.net/a.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/17/Screenshot-2025-12-14-at-20.48.34.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Video"/>
            <category term="Film and video"/>
            <category term="Experimental cinema"/>

        <updated>2024-02-29T14:58:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/17/Screenshot-2025-12-14-at-20.48.34.png" alt="" />
                    A+ explores the possibilities of problematising images and language that are explicitly&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/17/Screenshot-2025-12-14-at-20.48.34.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><strong><i>A+</i></strong><strong> </strong>explores the possibilities of problematising images and language that are explicitly political. One of the key methods in the <i>Media Blackout</i> <i>Series</i> is the development of a process of image negation that methodically ends in black; the duration of each piece is determined by the time this process takes. For <i>A+</i>, I employ a different method: rather than negating the image, the video gradually reveals a photograph while withholding part of the sound, which is then played backwards. In this way, the slogan is obliterated, giving way to other, unfixed meanings conveyed through the sounds of the protestors.</p>
<p>In contrast to <strong><i>Media </i></strong><strong><i>Blackout</i></strong><strong><i> I </i></strong>and <strong><i>Media Blackout III</i></strong>, <strong><i>A+</i></strong><strong> </strong>begins with abstraction and gradually reveals a figurative image. It draws on a well-known media image from the Gezi protests: a photograph of a grey-haired woman hurling a small stone with a catapult, combined with the sound of protestors from another protest in Turkey. As the image is fully revealed through zooming out, the sound of protestors chanting a slogan is gradually reduced. The video then further complicates the relationship between sound and image by playing them in reverse and layering them, following a predetermined process.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Forensic Architecture: The whole truth?</title>
        <author>
            <name>DJ</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://denizjohns.net/forensic-architecture-the-whole-truth.html"/>
        <id>https://denizjohns.net/forensic-architecture-the-whole-truth.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/13/Screenshot-2025-12-28-at-16.28.13.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="art criticism"/>
            <category term="Writing"/>

        <updated>2021-09-01T16:26:00+01:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/13/Screenshot-2025-12-28-at-16.28.13.png" alt="" />
                    Johns, Deniz (2021). "Forensic Architecture: The whole truth?" Millennium Film Journal 74&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/13/Screenshot-2025-12-28-at-16.28.13.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><strong>Johns, Deniz (2021). </strong>"Forensic Architecture: The whole truth?" Millennium Film Journal 74 “Fact/Artifact” Fall 2021 (peer-reviewed)</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Exhibition Catalogues &amp; Art Publications</title>
        <author>
            <name>DJ</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://denizjohns.net/exhibition-catalogues-and-art-publications.html"/>
        <id>https://denizjohns.net/exhibition-catalogues-and-art-publications.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/14/43849ABA-6897-4C15-9A4F-745B9D820ABC_1_105_c.jpeg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Writing"/>

        <updated>2020-01-28T17:17:00+00:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/14/43849ABA-6897-4C15-9A4F-745B9D820ABC_1_105_c.jpeg" alt="" />
                    Johns, Deniz et al (2025) In and On Contact, contribution to catalogue&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://denizjohns.net/media/posts/14/43849ABA-6897-4C15-9A4F-745B9D820ABC_1_105_c.jpeg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><a href="https://newartprojects.com/shop/nap_publications/in-and-on-contact/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Johns, Deniz </strong>et al (2025) <i>In and On Contact</i>, contribution to catalogue for the exhibition <i>Contact, </i>New Art Projects, London</a></p>
<p><a href="https://research.gold.ac.uk/id/eprint/30894/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Johns, Deniz </strong>et al (2022)<i> Responding to Women and Creativity, </i>Catherine Grant (ed.) CHELSEA space: London</a></p>
<p><a href="https://research.aub.ac.uk/id/eprint/251/1/Contact%20Festival.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Johns, Deniz </strong>et al (2016). Collective-iz Interview, <i>Contact Festival Publication </i>(Eds. S. Payne and A. Vallance)  </a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.sensesofcinema.com/2016/british-experimental/introduction-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Johns, Deniz </strong>and Payne, Simon (Eds.) (2016) A dossier on “Contemporary British Experimental Film and Video,” <i>Senses of Cinema </i>78th issue.</a></p>
<p><strong>Johns, Deniz </strong>et al (2016). Collective-iz artist statement. <i>Sequence Issue </i>4 (Ed. Simon Payne)</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
